Stockinette stitch slip tuck lace, all of these stitch
patterns make beautiful Fabrics each has its
own characteristics.
But which one uses more yarn?
It's important to understand patterns Stitch construction
to make yarn substitutions follow
along as we experiment to see which Stitch type
will put a limited amount of yarn to best use.
Let's say you have a partial cone of yarn and
you want to make a simple rectangular shawl.
How do you know if you have enough yarn?
Your best bet is to knit a Swatch and work out your
calculations from your Swatch look for the knit it
now tutorial estimating yarn requirements
part 1 for instruction.
Watch stitch pattern will stretch
that partial cone the farthest.
Should you knit in stockinette tuck lace.
Let's take a look and see each one of these swatches
is 100 stitches by 100 rows the chart shows the
weight the size and the square inches.
Let's use this information to estimate how
much yarn will need to knit our shawl.
Our stockinette Swatch measures 108 square
inches and it weighs 26 grams.
Now if we do the math, we know that we need
1890 square inches for our shawl.
If we divide those total square inches by the square
inches in our Swatch we get a multiplier of 17.5.
We need 17 and 1/2 swatches to
make up our whole shawl.
17 and a half times the 26 grams tells us
that we need 455 grams for our show.
Let's look at slip our slip stitch Swatch
is only sixty point five square inches.
Again, if we do the math divide the total square
inches of our shawl there Swatch measurement.
Gives us a multiplier.
So it's going to take 31 a little over thirty one
of those swatches to make an entire shawl.
The bottom line here is will need
625 grams for our shawl.
The lace stitch pattern that I chose is a hundred
and twelve square inches for my swatch.
This time we do the math will find that it
only takes 438 grams to knit our shawl.
It's probably not a surprise that a lace pattern will
use less yarn than other stitch patterns or
looking at it.
Another way a lace pattern will knit a larger
piece with the same amount of yarn.
We tested for random stitch patterns for comparison,
but do keep in mind that a two row tuck stitch
pattern were will vary greatly
from a four row tuck Stitch.
A lace pattern with one or two eyelets of every 10 rows
or so will be very different than our sample lace
pattern.
So use the are examples is the comparison of the techniques
and keep in mind the differences when
you're making a stitch pattern selection.
This concept is invaluable for every
Knitter both hand and machine.
I hope you add it to your bag of tricks.
Happy netting.